# Gökhan Çiflikli Curriculum Vitae

Department of Methodology
London School of Economics and Political Science
Houghton St
London, WC2A 2AE, UK
Phone:
Email:
Website:
GitHub:

# Research Interests

I'm a computational social scientist specialising in applied predictive modelling. My core research focuses on prediction of armed conflict using ensemble models; problematisation of the fidelity vs. interpretability trade-off in machine learning; quantitative text analysis and natural language processing of time-series data; and the measurement and quantification of issues of representation and bias in social sciences.

+44 7477-104110

gokhan.io

g.ciflikli@lse.ac.uk

github.com/ciflikli

# Professional Experience

# Research Appointments

2019-present **Postdoctoral Researcher**. *Automation of the Uppsala Conflict Data Program using NLP*. PI Prof. Kristine Eck. Department of Peace and Conflict Research, Uppsala University.

2018-present **Postdoctoral Researcher**. *Developing a GUI for the Quantitative Analysis of Textual Data*. PI Prof. Kenneth Benoit. Department of Methodology, London School of Economics.

2015-2016 **Researcher.** *Quantifying Political Violence in India: Real-time analysis and estimation.* International Institute for Strategic Studies, London.

2012-2014 **Researcher.** *Geo-Referencing Event Data for the Uppsala Conflict Data Program.* Department of Peace and Conflict Research, Uppsala University.

### Degrees

2018. Ph.D. International Relations, London School of Economics and Political Science. Learning Conflict Duration: Insights from Predictive Modelling

Examiners: Prof. Kristin Bakke (UCL) and Prof. Håvard Hegre (Uppsala University)

2017. Visiting Student Researcher Political Science, University of California, Berkeley.

2012. M.SSc. Peace and Conflict Studies, Uppsala University.

2008. B.A. International Relations, Kocaeli University.

# Data and Predictive Modelling Projects

2018-present **Researcher**. *Predictive GIS Analysis for the UN Peacekeeping Mission in CAR* with John Karlsrud, Allard Duursma, and Luke Abbs. United Nations.

2018 **Research officer.** *State of the States: Pooling Data for the 2018 U.S. Midterm Elections* U.S. Centre, LSE.

2017 **Developer.** *Interactive App for Forecasting Radical-Islamist Terrorist Attacks in the U.K.* Alan Turing Institute and the U.K. Cabinet Office.

2017 **Research assistant.** Visualising Endogenous Modernisation and Post-Communist Support for Democracy with Prof. Tomila Lankina and Prof. Alexander Libman. LSE.

2016-2018 **Research assistant.** *Measuring International Security via NYT: The Geopolitical Slack Index* with Prof. Peter Trubowitz. LSE.

2015-2017 **Research assistant.** *Predicting the Escalation and Severity of Armed Conflict* with Prof. Nils Metternich. University College London.

# Certificates

2017 Introduction to Complexity. Santa Fe Institute.

2016 PGCertHE Associate Level. LSE.

2015 ICPSR Summer Program in Quantitative Methods of Social Research. University of Michigan.

2013 Advanced Quantitative Methods and Research Design. Uppsala University.

#### **Publications**

#### Peer-Reviewed Articles

2018. Phull, Kiran, Gokhan Ciflikli and Gustav Meibauer. 'Gender and bias in the International Relations curriculum: Insights from reading lists'. *European Journal of International Relations*. First Published August 20, 2018.

#### Works in Progress

Ciflikli, Gokhan. 'Unpacking the Machine Learning Black Box: Locally Faithful Explanations'.

Ciflikli, Gokhan. 'A Unitary Predictive Model of Conflict Duration'.

Ciflikli, Gokhan and Nils Metternich. 'Taking time seriously when evaluating predictions in Binary-Time-Series-Cross-Section-Data'.

Metternich, Nils, Gokhan Ciflikli, Ali Altaf, and Tatjana Stankovic. 'Predicting the Severity of Civil Wars: An Actor-centric Approach'.

Trubowitz, Peter, Gokhan Ciflikli, and Kohei Watanabe. 'Measuring Geopolitical Risk using Automated Extraction of Newspaper Reports.'

Ciflikli, Gokhan and Kristine Eck. 'Improving the Granularity of Event Data using Quantitative Text Analysis'.

Ciflikli, Gokhan, Karsten Donnay, and Nils Metternich. 'Complexity Theories and the Prediction of Dynamic Conflict Systems'.

Ciflikli, Gokhan, Gustav Meibauer, and Kiran Phull. 'Social Citation: How Social Trends Influence the Dissemination of Scientific Articles'.

#### Book Reviews

2017. 'Computational Social Science: Discovery and Prediction', Michael Alvarez (ed.), *Political Studies Review*, Volume 15, Issue 4.

#### Non Peer-Reviewed Publications

2018-present Blog on predictive modelling, machine learning, and data visualisation for R statistical software at gokhan.io

2018 'A new interactive tool can show us just how polarised Congress has become.' *USApp: American Politics and Policy Blog.* 

2018 'Male authors outnumber their female counterparts on international relations course reading lists by more than five to one.' LSE Impact of Social Sciences Blog.

2015 'Indian government signs a historic peace accord with the Naga insurgents.' *International Institute for Strategic Studies*.

# Awards, Scholarships, and Grants

Sir Patrick Gillam Fieldwork Scholarship. Gillam Fund Committee. LSE. 2017. 3,000 GBP.

University of California, Berkeley Bursary. LSE Ph.D. Mobility Program. 2016. 2,300 GBP.

Social Research Methods Grant. International Relations Department, LSE. 3,000 GBP.

Michael Leifer Ph.D. Scholarship. LSE. 2014-2017. 100,000 GBP.

Collaborator. 'Facilitating Data Visualisation and Extraction: A New Interface for the Uppsala Conflict Data Program'. 2014. 2.4 million SEK (approx. 211,000 GBP).

# Teaching Experience

#### Data Science

**Introduction to Data Science and Big Data Analytics.** Lecturer and seminar teacher. *LSE Summer School*. 2018-2019.

**Special Topics in Quantitative Analysis: Quantitative Text Analysis.** Teaching assistant. *Postgraduate. Department of Methodology, LSE*. 2018-2019.

#### Quantitative Methods and Maths

**Game Theory I.** Teaching assistant. *Department of Mathematics, LSE*. 2016-2017.

**Executive Global MSc in Management Quantitative Dissertation Supervision.** Project officer. *Post-graduate. Department of Management, LSE.* 2016-2017.

**Introduction to SPSS and Stats.** Lecturer. LSE GROUPS. 2015-2016.

#### Political Science

Building Democracies from Conflict. Seminar teacher. LSE Summer School. 2016-2018.

**Public Choice and Politics**. Teaching assistant. *Department of Government, LSE*. 2015-2016.

# Presentations

# Conference Papers

2019. ISA, EPSA, APSA, POLTEXT.

2018. ISA, PSA Political Methodology Group Annual Conference.

2017. MPSA, ISA, APSA.

2016. APSA, Conflict Research Society, ISA.

2015. Conflict Research Society, Peace Science Society (International).

## Workshops

2018. Workshop on Forecasting Political Violence. University College London.

2018. ViEWS: A Political Violence Early Warning System Workshop. Uppsala University.

2018. Instructor. Applied Predictive Modelling in R Workshop. LSE.

#### Invited Talks

2019. 'Making Machine Learning Predictions More Human-Friendly: Locally Faithful Explanations'. Uppsala University.

# **Fieldwork**

#### Sierra Leone (January-March 2017)

Interviews with officers and rank-and-file of the Sierra Leone Army (SLA), ex-combatants belonging to the Revolutionary United Front (RUF), defence ministry and national security advisers, aid workers, Western diplomats and local journalists in Freetown, Hastings, and Makeni.

## Professional Service

#### Peer-Review

Reviewer for Political Analysis, Conflict Management and Peace Science and Journal of Peace Research.

## Memberships

American Political Science Association, Computational Social Science London Initiative, Conflict Research Society, International Studies Association, Midwest Political Science Association and Peace Science Society.

# Language Skills

Languages: English (fluent), Turkish (native)

Statistical Packages: SPSS, STATA (instructor)

Programming Languages: R (developer), Python

Front-end: HTML, CSS

Database Management: SQL